MICHAEL BALLARD

Front End Developer





An ambitious front end developer with 4 years of experience React development, I help create business critical web applications with modern technology from serverless to in house API's, crafting clean responsive UI's for the modern web.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Front End Developer

onejourney | December 2021-Present

- Helped launch a MLP (Minimum Lovable Product) for an established hospitality agency branching out into the platform space.
- Worked with a team of front end and back end developers to fix bugs, update legacy code and add new features for clients and in house support teams.
- Worked with the design team to craft an in house design system and components library.

Full Stack Developer

Cushon | September 2021-December 2021

- Worked in an agile team to deliver a new administration portal with NextJS.
- Contributed to development of a components library to be used by all development teams within the web and mobile app products.
- Performed code reviews for team mates within github and discussed best practices.
- Took part in discussions on best practice and coding standards to improve code quality.
- Aided younger developers with bugs and queries.

Front End Lead - Operational Intelligence

Vodafone I July 2020 - August 2021

- Lead front end of in house development for applications used by network engineers and support teams within the UK business.
- Transformed the front end development stack of the team from traditional MVC to React, with a decoupled API backend.
- Created a reusable components library for the team to utilise in order to make development easier as well as getting a consitent look and feel across our web estate.
- Implemented new development tools in the team to enforce coding standards and detect bugs, reducing risk of errors and increasing quality of written code.
- Created automated code deployments using Azure Devops CI/CD pipelines to remove the need to upload files to servers manually, and also enforced better use of Git version control utilising changelogs and branch releases.
- Ran workshops with the wider organisation to demo our technology transformation, sharing best practices and learnings.

Graduate Techboost Project

Vodafone | December 2019 - July

- Developed a React Native application to provide new starters with a smooth and user friendly onboarding experience.
- Ran workshops for my team to introduce them to mobile app development and React Native.
- Led development for the app and helped members of the team with issues they encountered.
- Took part in UX and UI workshops with senior developers in Vodafone to learn best practice and get feedback from professionals.

Solutions Engineer - IoT

Vodafone | September 2019 - July 2020

- Developed IoT solutions for customers using JavaScript on our Invent platform.
- Integrated with 3rd party APIs to expand our IoT capability.
- Involvement in client workshops to understand requirements and interate projects in an agile
- Ran workshops with the team to introduce them to various technologies such as React Native, Microsoft Flow and Python programming.

Automation Developer - Big Data Platforms & Services

Vodafone | April - September 2019

- Prototyped various machine learning solutions as a POC for reducing manual effort across the Big Data space.
- Developed an intent-analyis algorithm in Python which was used on support tickets to predict with 95% accuracy what department a ticket should be allocated to.
- Aided in development of a Machine Learning model to predict the closure category of tickets.
- Demoed prototypes to senior managers to demostrate the value of automated solutions.

PPMO Coordinator - Vodafone Business

Vodafone | September 2018 - March 2019

- Aided project managers with issues that arose with clients or project teams.
- Developed a reporting dashboard using SAP Business Objects to allow senior managers to get an overview of their project teams and areas of concern.
- Created a website to showcase a new file sharing capability within the department.
- Automated some data entry tasks using Python to allow realocation of resources.

Junior Developer

Gloversure | August 2016 - May 2017

- My first professional experience of web and mobile app design.
- Developed a mobile app using the lonic framework for customers to be able to manage their site content from their phone.
- Developed a PHP application to enable the marketting team to create mobile notifications for customers.
- Modernised a lot of legacy code. Most noteably AJAXified the CMS to enable dynamic content and less page redirects.

SKILLS

Technical

JavaScript, TypeScript, React, NextJS

Serverless/cloud, AWS, GCP

UI/UX

Github, version control, CI/CD pipelines, automated deployment, devops

Docker, containerisation

Chakra UI, custom components libraries

State management, redux, recooil, mobx

Professional

Effective communicator

Confident leader

Willingness to help others

Good time management

Agile practices, kanban boards, standups, retrospectives etc.

Other skills

Photography and Filming

Photoshop and Video editing

Good knowledge of PC Hardware

Inevitably acting as tech support for my whole family

EDUCATION

BSc in Computer Science

Aberystwyth University 2014 - 2018

Warwick School

GCSE and A Level 2007 - 2014

LANGUAGES

English (Native)

INTERESTS

Photography

Mountain biking

Gaming

Warhammer

Stock markets and investing

Anything Elon Musk is doing